It's completely feasible that you won't
have programming languages.
>> This is Roberto, the creator of the Lua
programming language, and I asked him
all about programming language design.
>> C++ I think is a good example of a
language that is really, really complex.
And JavaScript I think it's even worse.
I always joke that the JavaScript the
good part here
a very thin book comparatively official
JavaScript book.
>> Given how [snorts] much AI has been
progressing, would you still recommend
people learn computer science today?
>> If you really think about that, it's
really difficult to recommend people
learning anything.
>> Here's the full episode.
In 2023, Lua was the second highest
programming language by growth according
to contributors on GitHub.
And I saw that it was also used in
famous games like World of Warcraft and
Roblox. And so, I wanted to ask you what
kind of programming language is Lua and
what sets it apart?
>> Lua is a language that you usually use
together with combined it with another
language like C or C++ and then you have
an architecture where
Lua takes care of the more dynamic part
of your program, things that change more
frequently, things that are are not so
resource intensive, the the hard parts
you have written in C or C++. So, it's
typically what is called a scripting
language.
There is a some confusion I think
between scripting languages and dynamic
languages. And people just I think
consider that a dynamic language to be
more or less the same thing as a
scripting language.
And they are not exactly the same thing.
So, for instance, a big difference
between Lua and several other scripting
languages is that
for scripting, you have two typical
uses. You can have the the the that I
call who has the main loop.
So, you can you can have the program
written in C
and calling Lua
or you have your program written in Lua
calling C.
And for several
called scripting languages are actually
you
you don't have to, but it's much more
easy to use if you have your program
written in the scripting language and C
language is only for your libraries.
And Lua is very good fit when you want
the reverse. You want the the the the
program written in C and then you you
have calls Lua from time to time. So,
the point is that Lua is very good at
this that you have the the the main loop
the the the program written in C and
then it calls Lua for some tasks or for
whatever you you you want to do. And for
instance, in games, this is very
important to keep the the frame ratio of
the game. So, for instance, you have the
loop the loop keeps the rhythm of
[snorts] the game and keeps everything
and then at every frame it calls Lua
Lua's updates all characters all images
everything in in the game and then it
return to C to do the renderization etc.
So,
it is a very good fit. But, the main
point is that that it people sometimes
call this the embedding
versus extending. So, you can extend the
scripting language with C or you can
then can embed the scripting language
into C.
And so may several languages are very
good only for extending while Lua is
really good for both embedding and
extending.
>> Why is Lua good for embedding and Python
it's almost the opposite?
>> Because in Lua since the beginning Lua
was thought about Lua as a library.
Since the beginning Lua was written as a
library. So I think that's the the main
difference. Lua has a standalone program
that I mean you can call Lua in your
console, in your common line, but that
program is just a client of the official
client of the library following the the
same API that any other program can use.
So this idea of language as a library, I
think it's not very common. It's
something that is very particular in
Lua.
>> When you design a language as a library,
what are the unique, I guess, um,
design decisions?
>> I think that goes
a lot of small
small and big details. For instance,
your your idea of what is your global
space or your about scopes of variables,
about exception handling. For instance,
it's very important that it's very
common in Lua that you raise an
exception in Lua but catch the exception
in C. So all these things about how you
do exception handling in the language.
Another
It's not a big deal but it's a For
instance, most dynamic languages, that's
almost a
definition of a dynamic language. They
have an eval
function that you can give a piece of
code and then it executes that code.
In Lua we don't instead of eval we have
a function that we call the load.
That you give a piece of code and it
returns a function
an internal function like it was a Lua
function that when you call that
function, then you execute
the the associated code. It does doesn't
execute immediately. So, you have this
clear separation between
compiling like the the Lua code that you
have and then you can do that in C. So,
in C, you can get a piece of Lua code,
you can compile it, check if it has
errors, etc. Then you call that for
instance for instance a different piece
or you can even call several times. For
instance, you can load functions from
Lua into C, you keep them I mean in the
Lua
space and then you can call that same
function again and again. It's not a big
difference, of course, because for if
you have a value, you can evaluate a
function declaration and then returns
that function. So, you you can If you
have a value, you can do load. If you
have load, you can do eval. But I think
load it's
it's simpler to use for that kind of
thing that is when you think about
libraries for instance. In Lua, you it
doesn't have a global state. I think
that's a I forgot that that that's a
very important difference.
When C starts, the first thing it has to
do is to call create a new Lua state.
And then everything you do, you do on
that state.
And that state is completely
independent
of everything else. So, C can for
instance create another Lua state and
both states are completely independent,
completely there is no communication
between them. And so this again shows
that the
And so for instance, C can use a state
to do a lot of stuff and then it can
close the state and all memory used by
Lua released everything that Lua was
using is released. For instance, if C
doesn't need to use Lua anymore for a
program, you release all
all resources used by Lua and your
program in C continues and then later it
can again create another state, etc. So
there's as I said there is several small
or not so small decisions in the
language but all the time we think about
the language as
is that good for embedding? Is that
possible to to do embedding and things
like that?
>> When you think of the programming
community generally, everyone is quite
familiar with Python but not as familiar
with Lua. I thought it might be
interesting
to compare the two languages. So if you
compared Lua to Python, what are the
pros and cons of each language design?
>> Lua is a language that is intended to be
used
in in this idea for of
scripting architecture.
So the Lua for instance, it doesn't try
having a lot of different libraries.
If you have something that oh I want to
write a a quick program for something
that Python is much better. It has all
the libraries you can dream about it. It
has a lot of libraries built-in
already into the language. So that the
language is huge. It's I mean the the
installation it's it's a huge so
the
download etc. But it
it has exactly oh I need that. Oh, it's
there. I need that. It's there. And Lua
is almost the opposite. Some very
minimalistic language because they did
that thing embed Lua into your program.
It doesn't use almost any resources.
Most of the libraries, the important
libraries that you you will use will be
provided by the program itself. It will
be the commands like you move a
character or do some speech or things
like that from the engine of of the game
for in for instance if you think about
games, but whatever it is. So, Lua is I
think that's the the main big
difference. It's They they have very
different goals.
>> I saw some benchmarks and I saw that Lua
is much faster than Python. Why is that?
>> That that
Those benchmarks are are not exactly,
but I think that the main point is
exactly One things that Lua does have
these
focus on on performance. Again, in the
realm of scripting languages doesn't
want to compete with C or C++. But in
the realm of dynamic mostly now it's
dynamic language, not scripting
languages. We have some focus on
performance. So, I think this is a a
first difference. Python is exactly is
much more I think that it's a a decision
that they make. Performance is not that
important. It's more important to be
flexible, to be easy to do whatever you
want to do. That in Lua sometimes we do
not put some features because we think
that there is no way to implement that
efficiently. But also I think some part
of that performance difference comes
exactly because of the the size of Lua.
So, most of the virtual machine fits in
your cache for instance. I think there
is these two big things. One is that Lua
doesn't have so many features. It's not
so dynamic as Python. So, in Python
there is a lot of in the interactions
because everything can mean something
else. In Ruby, we are a little more
conservative on that side. And but I
think also this thing of being small
also makes it naturally faster.
>> So, on the distinction between scripting
languages and dynamic or I guess it
seems like dynamic language is a
superset. Scripting language is a is a
subset of that. Am I understanding that
JavaScript is a dynamic language, not a
scripting language from your
perspective?
>> Yes, exactly. Yes, exactly. Because the
scripting it came the the the the the
original scripting language it was bash
or the shells from Unix. Of this idea
that there's a language that coordinates
other stuff. So, for instance, it can be
extending again, you can use But the
this idea that you have
two different language for instance, in
in the shell is only useful because you
have a lot of programs written in C
that are controlled by shell. So, the
scripting language has this very strong
idea that you have this idea of a dual
language architecture. This is So,
scripting means it's like it is it's the
name scripting. It means you it's like a
the you coordinator. You you give a
script to be executed by
those other other things.
>> You gave a talk a while ago and someone
asked you a question of, you know, what
books do you recommend for, you know,
studying programming languages? And you
said actually
that you enjoyed studying the language
design of other programming languages.
>> I like reading books that describe the
design of
of the languages. I I think the
best books are those written by the
author of a language about the design of
that language.
>> What book recommendation do you think is
best on language design?
>> JavaScript the good parts, for instance.
The the the it's
kind of old now, but I think that's I
think it's a very interesting book.
Although I always joke that the
JavaScript the good part
a very thin book comparatively.
>> Official JavaScript books like
>> one hand of the language is the good
parts.
But but I I think that book is really
interesting like because exactly it it
discussed the language it discusses in
the bad parts and it focus on the good
parts but then explains why it's there,
why it it was made that way, etc. That
is a book that I like.
>> When we were talking about Lua, it
sounds like one of the things that sets
Lua apart is the performance and how
minimal it is.
And when I was reading about Lua, I saw
that there's Lua Jit. How does the Lua
Jit work?
>> Lua Jit
the first thing that's completely
different project. It doesn't have
anything to do with us. But it's a
incredible piece of of software that is
is a just-in-time compiler for Lua
that's and I think exactly one of the
reasons
it works so well on top of Lua is
because of the simplicity
of
Lua. It's a very regular language. I
mean it has a very as I said it doesn't
have many exceptions or too many
indirections or things that so it's not
that dynamic. I mean everything can mean
something completely different. So that
I think that gives a very good language
for a Jit. But the the the the the Mike
Paul is the name of the the the guy that
made the the in the I think he's still
working on that on the first legit. He's
It's unbelievable his work.
>> What makes writing a legit difficult?
>> The first thing that for me I don't want
to get involved with legit is because
it's machine dependent. It's not very
productive. I mean, you you do a lot of
work and it only works on that
architecture. And then I want to running
another architecture. But, Mike Paul he
created a kind of
pseudo pseudo assembler that he writes
in this assembly and then he translates
that assembler through real machine
pulled of the different machines. So,
trying to unify the different
architectures. So, there is a a lot of
work, but I I don't like it. I I think
architecture I
I like to study, but I don't like to to
to to work with because I think it's
very unstable. Each new version they
change that or they change that the I
mean they they change the ABI for
something and then now the stack has to
be aligned in in some very
particular way. And so
And [clears throat] the of course also
to to get that performance that he gets
he made the what's called the trace
compiler. The idea of a trace compiler
that instead of a function
and compiling a function
it could it works like a
any legit that it tries to detect things
that are executed frequently. And so it
starts what's called a trace. It it gets
recording everything that the code is
doing including function calls, etc.
Until it closes the loop.
And then it compiles that loop
including function calls, etc.
Everything in line. It com-
compiles that for that specific, for
instance, so that number of happened to
be an integer, so it compiles after the
number will be an integer again, and
there is a lot of checks just check if
everything is as assumed, and then it
executes the loop. And then this is
very, very, very fast. But anything that
is different, for instance, you call
again that you call it frequently with
integers, and suddenly you call through
with a float, then at some part of the
code it's it is
it breaks the the the condition, and you
have to to return to the interpreter
part, and I think that's one of the
worst parts is that you you have to
translate the state that it's all
compressed into registers, etc. For
instance, you don't even have a call
stack because you didn't
do the call you didn't do the calls, you
just inlined it. But then, oops,
something went wrong. Now you have to
continue interpreting, so you have to
recreate the stack that you didn't
create originally, etc. So, I mean, I
even
>> [laughter]
>> even to think about that I have
headaches.
>> Standard Lua is portable, but to execute
on a machine, it eventually gets
converted into machine instructions
somewhere. Where in the stack is it
eventually translated to machine
instructions?
>> Lua is written in C. The interpreter is
written in C, and then you so you you
compile that into machine code, the
interpreter, the Lua code. Then the
point when you get some some
some I mean, the Lua code the Lua
interpreter code. When you get some Lua
code,
you do what is we call a
pre-compilation,
that is we we translate to an internal
language,
and then the interpreter is just a big
loop.
It's a loop with a switch. I mean,
that's a a very big simplification, but
that that in in general terms, a loop
with a switch that get instruction,
does a switch, and see all this
instruction is the instructions are
quite similar to a CPU. Move that, but
then instead of creating it executes
that structure. Move Move A to B, so it
it does a
move A to B and executes that, and again
repeats, executes the next instruction.
So, this is how a interpreter works and
basically, so we we precompile a Lua.
There is a compilation, but we compile
for this virtual machine,
and then we have this main
interpreter loop that people call that
just fetch each instruction. So, a jump
is just a jump. You have an array of of
byte codes. A jump will just go to that.
You have a
a counter that tells where you are in
this array. A jump you just update that
counter. It goes to another position of
that array where you're going to So,
it's like you s-
you emulate the CPU in software. It's
written in C,
the the interpreter. This main loop is
written in C.
So, if you compile it in Linux, it will
run in Linux or in a
X86
architecture, it will run in that
architecture. If you compile that in the
Mac, it will run in the Mac. It's a C
program.
>> Got it. Okay, so and that's that's the
part that's not portable, and the C
compiler handles that.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. The all portability of
Lua comes on top of portability of C.
>> How does JIT compare to ahead-of-time
compilation in terms of performance?
>> Both ahead-of-time Any kind of
compilation is easily not easily, but it
can be 10 times faster than interpreting
or even 100 times faster than
interpreting depending what you were are
doing. But 10 times is a very good
figure. Between ahead-of-time and
trace compilation, then depends a lot of
what you are doing.
After trace compilation is particularly
good for
benchmarks.
Because you're repeating it more or less
they are very uniform. You are doing
exactly the same thing again and again
and again. So, then trace compilers
shine. They I mean this is the best they
can do.
In real programs, that's
depends a lot, but but but you I
wouldn't say there is a clear winner
between the two. I think depends a lot
of the kind of problem.
>> Is it possible to write an ahead-of-time
compiler for Lua?
>> Yes, there are there are
several.
None I mean I think I don't not sure if
there is anyone on production quality,
but for research etc. there are several.
I I have a student who wrote one like a
master thesis. We did
simple Lua compiler ahead-of-time Lua
compiler or something like that. The
exactly because it was just
[clears throat] it gets these opcodes
and expands into
into C code and then you
send that through through a C compiler
and then you have a head of time comp
head of time compiler for Lua and it
gave like three five times boosting
performance. You very very
as the title said it's like ridiculous
simple compiler.
>> I always hear there's there's compiled
languages and there's dynamic or
interpreted languages I guess.
But really that distinction is in the
tool chain not necessarily in the way
that the symbols are laid out on the
source code. Like I could write compiler
or program that takes in Python code and
then converts it into machine code and
then I would have compiled Python.
>> And you can interpret C code too. You
can write an interpreter for C.
Yes. But the the main difference is
exactly what it's easy to For instance,
as I said, one of the hallmarks of
interpreted languages is the eval. So,
if you want to compile the language and
keep eval, you have to
have a compiler as a library of your
of your runtime because you may want to
compile things
during execution. This is the hallmark
of a dynamic language. That's all. You
can create code while running code. So,
that part is that that's why
more much more often than not
dynamic languages are interpreted.
But you can compile but then sometimes
or some compilers do not handle eval at
all. They say, "Oh, you can compile as
long as your program doesn't have
evals." The so there is some
restrictions. And as I said, you can
interpret C code I mean, but you'll be
extremely slowly with it doesn't but
>> I think one big difference I when I look
at statically or you know static
languages or compiled languages
they they seem to have type systems in
them or the type annotations.
What is the role of a type system in the
compilation process?
>> Depends a lot of the on the type system.
The several type systems like in C for
instance are written to be an very
important part of the compilation
process. So if you have the right type
system is much much easier to write a
compiler.
A trivial example is when the space for
variables because if you know all this
is an integer, this is a float, this is
a double, you know exactly how many
bytes of memory you need to that.
Otherwise it's a massive more often than
not you have to keep everything in the
heap dynamically allocated and so
huge
penalty in performance. And for instance
when you see it as I said a trivial you
have an addition.
A plus B. If you know the type of A
A plus B, you have the type of A, the
type of B, you have a compile time you
know all this plus is a
I'm adding two integers. I just generate
the machine code to add integers and
there everything it's fine. In a dynamic
language as here plus
I don't I I I compile
to a virtual in the virtual language it
is just piece of plus but then how do I
at run time you have to check what is A?
Oh, A is an integer, B is a float. Oh, I
have to convert or B is a string or
depending on the language you're if
you're not doing addition you can be
doing concatenation or you can just
calling some and you have to do all that
at runtime. So, types can be very, very
important to compile efficiently, but of
course you have to
have a type system that
that there are several language now like
type type script that the
types are kind of
you do not guarantee that everything has
the types you said
they have. So, then it's impossible to
use them to compile because oh, probably
will be an integer, but if it's not I
mean it's if it I have an integer
register to put 20
it must be a register or
things will not work. So, but if you
have the right type system they are
essential for a good compilation.
>> I know some programming languages have
type inference, but if you did you ran
type inference and you got a unambiguous
set of types and then you use that in
compilation. Like could you do that for
Lua?
>> Nope.
I mean that's not computable, but a lot
of people tried to to do
in type inference for dynamic languages
and it's really hard pro problem and
it's very difficult to do anything
useful in terms of performance. What you
sometimes you get but you have a very
restrict
If you write your program in that
specific way use for So, it's like you
don't have the type but you write the
program thinking about type and then if
the program is that very particular
format, then you can
do type inference and everything goes
well. Otherwise, either type inference
doesn't work, or I mean, it works, but
it actually it infers very generic types
for everything, and so you cannot take
advantage of of of the types. Because
exactly the dynamic nature of the
language. This This also happens if Lua
JIT, for instance.
You can get much much better performance
if you have a kind of a type system in
your in your mind. Usually, we do that,
and you and you follow that type rules
even without a type I mean, the compiler
the language does not impose them on
you, but you assume, "Oh, I'm going to
follow those some type discipline. I'm
not going to to to use the same variable
to store integers and strings, etc." And
then you can have much better results.
>> OpenAI, [snorts]
Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel all use
this product to make their lives better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an ad product, and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSL, there's SCIM, there's RBA,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product, and you want to sell to
other
WorkOS will solve all of these critical
feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started, and I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. Earlier you
mentioned that Lua can call C, and C
could call Lua. And
you mentioned we talked about the the
compiler and the interpreter, and how do
these pieces work together in the case
where you're chaining different
programming languages?
>> Yeah, the the the main trick, I mean,
it's not a trick, the technique
for Lua calling C is a C pointers.
Function pointers. There is a pointer to
a function.
This is part of the official C
language. So, when you start Lua,
suppose you are in C, yeah, as I said,
you create a library.
Uh all right, you create a state, a Lua
state, and then you can register, you
send to Lua
C pointers, so function pointers, I
mean, pointers to functions in your C
library. Associated with names, Lua
stores that in some data structure.
Okay, so it says, "Oh, the function sign
is associated with that pointer, etc."
So, when it's it's doing the
interpretation, "Oh, this instruction is
call, instruction call. Let's see what
it's calling. Oh, it's calling A. What
is the value of A? Oh, it's a pointer to
and then it calls that pointer." And
then we do the call the the the C
function to do that.
And the when when C wants to call Lua, I
I mean,
a Lua function is just a data structure
from the point of view of of C, just an
array of byte codes of up codes, and
then it's calls the Lua interpreter
function, "Oh,
please interpret that function for me."
So, C can call Lua to interpret that
function, and that function is running,
and then can call a C function using a
pointer, and you can have that in the
stack several levels. So, you are
running a Lua function that calls C, and
C calls Lua again, and Lua calls C, and
you have recursive stuff in that, etc.
And everything works and it's just
just works.
>> In one of your talks on Lua, you
mentioned that there's security benefits
to using a scripting language. What are
those benefits and how does it protect
the hardware?
>> It's not only hardware. Once I I I gave
a talk here in in Brazil. I was called
it to to give a talk in a PyCon
a PyCon they they called the Python
conference in Brazil. They called me for
a talk. At the end of the talk I said,
"Oh, Lua is we use it as a scripting
language." As I said, emphasizing that
thing that you have this dual language
architecture and we I I know of case of
Lua being used with C, with C++,
with Fortran, with several different
languages. And then someone in the
audience says, "Oh, we also
use Lua for scripting Python programs."
And what what's that the case? They they
they have a huge Python program
for financial stuff that has a do a lot
of financial transactions, etc. And they
wanted to do script I mean to have a
like
a common line where you could write
instructions to be executed by the the
at runtime, for instance, for debugging
or for inspecting, for
whatever you need some kind of end-user
programming.
But they said exactly what I was talking
about spaces. In Python,
basically, if you have a common line
then you're going to run Python, that
Python can do whatever it wants to do
in your program. There is no way to
protect. So, if you gave that to the
user, the user could do whatever it
wanted to do.
I mean
for the program. And so, the program
would break a lot of invariants of a lot
of important stuff in the files it kept,
etc. And so, what they did, they gave
the thinking Lua because as I said, as
Lua you create a state. For instance, as
I just mentioned, you can only call C
functions.
That's is true in Python again, but the
particularity You can only call C
functions if you give the C pointer
to Lua.
So, have a very strict or any there
there is very little as I said, there is
a library. When you create a Lua state,
it has
no functions at all.
There is nothing. I mean, you cannot
open files. Everything there are we call
standard libraries. Usually, you open
a state and you register those standard
libraries in Lua. So, you have the the
minimum like you have mathematical
functions, etc. But you can open a state
and has no functions at all in Lua.
It can only do things calling those
specific functions you you you gave. So,
they they used Lua to have this kind of
control. You can write Lua code here,
but that Lua code can only do very
specific things in the Python program.
You cannot call any Python function or I
mean, build any kind of Python data
structure, etc. So, was this a a nice
example. In the case of hardware, it's
the same thing. You cannot just go in
the For instance, there is a a port a
hardware port that controls the speed of
the fan
that that keeps the temperature of the
CPU. And if you put that very low, you
can really burn the CPU. I mean, because
the CPU gets very hot. And so, we've you
have a seat you cannot call C directly.
You must call Bingo, and only Lua has
access to that. So, if you can only
program in Lua, it's a doll Lua, then
you you check whether the the numbers
you are giving are are precise or
whatever it has to check, and then it
calls
>> It's kind of like a sandbox environment.
>> Yes, exactly. Yes, sandbox is the exact
word for that.
>> I saw there's this, I guess, paper,
maybe it was a
article you wrote on the history of Lua
with several other people, and I thought
there were some interesting quotes in
there I kind of wanted to ask you about.
So, um one of them
it says that there's this old joke that
says that a camel is a horse designed by
a committee.
>> Yes, that's not mine. That's a real
old joke.
>> Does that mean that you think the best
programming languages are designed by as
few people as possible?
>> Yes, I do think. Yes.
Because there's one thing that that it's
easy to to observe it it's is is this.
If you have a committee
writing a language,
everyone wants to put something
from themselves into the language. So,
you have that your favorite mechanism,
and you will fight whatever it takes to
put your favorite mechanism into the
language. And very few people will fight
against
putting anything in the language.
I mean, some people say, "Oh, no, this
is too much. This is too complicated."
But people fight much more fiercely for
to for put something they you in the
language, then
against putting something in the
language. So, when you have a committee,
the the tendency is so let's
keep adding stuff to let's keep adding
stuff, and people sometimes even do not
understand. I mean, they were not sure
if everybody there is really
know the language
well. Oh, well, I'm not putting that,
but that fits with all the parts of the
Oh, I didn't even know the language has
this other part. I mean, so
things sometimes do not fit together
very well, etc. So, first you have a
what's called a conceptual integrity.
It's a name that give that everything
fits together, everything
it's designed if
everything else in mind, etc. It's much
easier to Yeah, I'm not saying I mean,
Lua has several
wrong stuff regarding because of with
time, etc. There you make mistakes, but
it's much easier to get things
right if you have a small group of
people that everybody knows what
everybody else is thinking. I mean, you
are deciding whether to put something in
the language or not. It's much easier to
change your mind
if you do not put something, and then
later you decide to add it to the
language, than to add something, and
then later you decide, "Oh, I shouldn't
have
that was not a good idea." So, when in
doubt, our default is always don't put
it. If you're not very sure, don't put
it. We can always add that later, and so
keep the door open through to
change your mind.
>> I saw in the original Lua programming
language that there was no Boolean type,
and I've never seen that before. Why was
there no Boolean in the original Lua?
>> Well, C doesn't have Booleans.
I mean, the the the the original C and
C90 up to C99
using integers. If it's zero, it's
false. If it's different from zero, it's
true. And
and people lived quite well with
with that Lisp. I mean, there are
several languages that don't have
Booleans. And actually, we only put
Booleans in Lua
because we wanted false. True is
completely useless in Lua. Nobody used
true. And nobody such a joke, but it's
too strong, but
it's it's not very useful. You can use
almost any other value for true.
But the the the the the problem is that
the in Lua the the
nil, that special value nil,
is in a table. It is equivalent to the
key not being present.
You all think better that was a good
that
decision, but it's very embedded in the
design of the language. And it has with
this strong concept that a table
a key that is not present in
in a table that is an associative array,
it has a nil value. It's completely
indistinguishable
whether it's absent. I mean, absent
means it has a nil value. Nil valent
means it's absent. And so, sometimes you
want to have a false value. And but you
want to know what it is there in the
table. And so, we needed a false. To
have a false, you can put in the table
and it's completely different from being
absent. You know, there is a key and the
key has a false value. So, we needed a a
value. And if you're going to have a
false, then
we added true to maybe it would make
sense to have false without true, but
with true it's almost useless.
>> Why not use zero as false if you're okay
with one as true?
>> It could be we could have used it, but
that
Among other things, that would be a a
big change because exactly it didn't was
that way, so we we added that late here
in the language, so changing zero to
false would be a very big
incompatibility.
But it could be for instance in in in
Python, I think a lot of stuff are are
false. I mean, zero is false, empty list
is false, empty In JavaScript, I think
it's even worse. I I don't re-
don't recall exactly, but I mean
This is kind of arbitrary. I mean, you
we could have for instance
nil, false, zero, empty string. I mean,
it
It just depends the kind of test that
you use.
It's not
In dynamic languages, it's very easy.
>> Python has the like you're describing
the truthy values and the falsy values,
or I guess they can be interpreted as
false. And but it's it's more implicit,
less explicit, and I know JavaScript is
even further on that spectrum where you
can do some really weird stuff that
implicitly has some behavior. Do you
think that design direction is good or
bad?
>> It's like a small compact, it's more
easy to write stuff. And but you always
have this balance in any language is
almost anything. The more flexible you
you
the more flexibility you have,
the less
protection you have. In C, you have
something like like that. People do not
notice, but
because C's typed.
But, you can check whether an integer
is true or false.
You can check whether a float
is true or false directly because again
it checks whether the float is zero or
different from zero. You can check
whether a pointer is nil or different
from nil because in C nil is a magic
zero.
So, it's kind of if you do not write any
test, it has an implicit test like
different from zero.
And this zero can be a integer, can be a
float, can be a pointer. So, in C also
you have this kind of
flexibility. It's just that you have to
be more explicit usually.
This
avoids errors, but
so this you have always this balance
between
easy to write and
easy to make mistakes.
>> I saw that
Lua is one indexed instead of zero
indexed, and I I had never seen a
programming language like that in my
experience.
>> There was a lot of programming languages
like that.
>> So, yeah, why why is it one indexed?
>> Because everything in the real world are
one indexed. If you have a book, you
have the the chapter one, chapter two.
Nobody number chapters as zero, one,
two, three. Only program- programmers
are the only Even mathematicians, if you
get a mathematic book, a book of
mathematic, any sequence, it's A1 and
A2, A3. If you get a matrix, the first
element is A11, A12, and then A
Everything
is written with a Only
in programming language that is this of
zero.
And the funniest part is that for
instance Fortran
that now it's it's very old language,
but to index it from one. In Pascal you
can choose I mean you write an array,
you can say this array means index it
from minus five to five. And so it's
it's index it from whatever value you
want to whatever value
you want.
Zero became
extremely popular
because of C.
C uses zero and a lot of languages copy
kind of inspired by by by C. They have
the same operators, the same syntax for
expressions.
The Boolean
operators for instance that is not
standard mathematics. Almost all
languages chose the same operator A to Z
they are written in C.
And so a lot of language copied C and
then zero index it became very popular.
And what is funny
is that in C there is no indexing. In C
indexing is just an illusion
because what you have is pointer
arithmetic.
And C when you write A index it by I
actually what you are saying get the
contents of A plus Y.
And so because in C you don't have
indexing, you have
this
displacements or deltas I don't know how
offsets.
Then it must have index it by zero
because of that because then the first
element is the element that is at the
the original address. So
C doesn't have index indexing. So when
you say A is index by zero, it doesn't
index by zero because it doesn't index
by anything. But it it have this
illusion of indexing and then it's easy
to think that it
And then a lot of language that do not
use pointer arithmetic do not have this
restriction, do not have this semantics,
copy it C and kept the the zero indexing
as the thing. If you got a 12-year-old
and try to explain to them
the zero indexing,
I I assure it's much much easier for
them
to write, "Oh, I I have a list of the
first element." I always joke that is
the first element is zero. And you write
first you for one, but the first element
one
is not one, is zero.
So,
it has advantages zero for this first
some specific operators mathematically.
For instance, you want to do a circular
buffer, zero is better. There are some
small advantage, but it's much much more
confusing.
And as mIRC has this idea of end user
programming,
we always joke it's much easier to make
life easier for the non-programmers.
And I am sure that programmers can
program whatever index they have to do
because they are supposedly they are
professional. They can learn that all
indexing is from them to put all the end
user the burden and of using something
completely different from them indexing
by zero. What does it mean the element
index zero? They never saw and oh, are
the chapters in the book? Yes, the first
chapter is at zero, the second chapter
is at one. It
No, I'm not joking. When you try to
explain that to non-programmer, even
though
they don't need to be 12
I mean, just get anyone that is not
an internet programmer think, "Oh, I
have the absolute I mean, but they are
grown-up. You are
I mean, okay, you are a Christian. You
are
If zero and sure you can learn through
truth to program if one or minus one or
whatever it is the the base you have to
use them. Sure.
>> But do you think you see a lot of bugs
cuz um
maybe someone thinks it's zero.
>> Unfortunately, I see some bugs.
But as I always say, that's are the kind
of bugs that
just shows that you will be then do
minimum testing.
Because that kind of bug is not a kind
of that kind of bug that always you
try to anything you try to do
in a the way.
If you
start from zero or start from one, you
have a bug.
So, the the most simple test that you
can imagine to test anything related to
an array, to a list, etc. And if you if
you
mistake zero to one, you you detect
that. So, if you
have that kind of bug, it just shows
that you didn't
test that code at all.
>> There was this talk that you gave on the
cost of adding uh
language features to Lua and how there's
a lot of hidden costs. And I think it
today
um implementation cost of software is
going down due to, you know, AI code
generation or LLMs.
And I was wondering if that changes your
thinking on
um I guess the cost of adding features
to a programming language.
>> AI is something that
we don't really know what is going to
happen. If you go to an extreme
it's com- completely feasible
that we
we won't have programming languages. And
I mean
because if you did the AI is writing all
your code and is checking all your code
and doing everything, in a few years
maybe we don't need programming. AI can
write machine code directly, it doesn't
need programming languages. It
It's easier for for them to compile or
even generate the code directly. I mean,
I don't know what is going to happen in
a few years. So,
I
think it's very hard for me to
talk anything about AI because I have
and I think nobody have a clear idea
what I mean, people have a maybe a clear
idea what it happens in 1 year or 2
years, but in 5 years, I I mean, anyone
that says, "Oh, that's going to happen
in 5 years." It's just
I mean,
it's
just guess.
So,
I I think it's hard to to say anything.
This is all because of AI. So,
keeping the meaning thing, I mean, that
is still have the for instance the Oh,
why you still use programming languages?
Because if you want the the user or the
some
human to be able to check the result of
what the AI is doing etc. So, I still
think that most of the things about
programming language still hold. For
instance, the the the cost of complexity
of you understanding I mean, AI create a
code for you and then you really
understanding what that code does. I
mean, it's even worse. I mean, it's much
more important that the language should
be clear and and has a
not no hidden mechanisms because they I
may use a hidden mechanism it doesn't
have the concept oh that will be
difficult for a human to understand that
what is really happening here is is
something it's a something that for
instance oh I can use that but I'm for
sure it's going to put a comment here
because I'm sure that someone that reads
that in 1 month it's not going to
understand.
AI doesn't have that kind of
of
of thinking and so it just use that that
trick or that thing and it's so I think
the AI if you think about this idea of
AI generating code I think it's even
more important for the language to be
simple to be understandable for you to
be able to really understand that the
code that you are seeing does what you
think it should it should do it it
really understand what the code is
doing. So this thing about simplicity I
think it's it's very important. And
I think
the other part from the need maybe I may
facilitate documentation I'm not sure if
I need this thing about conceptual
integrity for instance to keep things oh
that makes sense etc. I really think
that one of the main costs is that it
it's the the the burden you put on the
user to learn
one more thing about it
your language.
So there's the other possibility I have
said that implementation is the that is
the the the part that AI can really
help you.
It's not a really re-
really important cost.
>> If you think about like a spectrum of
simple to complex, what programming
languages are, you know, the most simple
ones that you think of that are easy to
understand, less confusing side effects,
and what programming languages are the
most complex and have the most foot
guns?
>> This this famous quote comes from, I
don't know from whom, that the simplest
possible, but not simpler than that.
Because you see, if you go to the
extreme of simplicity, you could get for
instance lambda calculus or Turing
machines and say, "Oh, that's really
simple." I mean, this is really simple,
but it's completely impossible to to
write any program in that. I mean, if
you have really simple stuff, I think
the extremes would be like that, but you
don't want to be there. But for the
other side,
I think C++ I think is a good example of
a language that I think it's really
really complex.
>> A question that comes up a lot is
given how much AI has been progressing,
you know, would you still recommend
people learn computer science today?
>> If you really think about that, it's
really difficult to recommend people
learning anything
for a profession. I mean, we have no
idea what AI will do in 5 years. If
someone is entering university now, they
are going to graduate in 4 years, 5
years, or
I think maybe three three and a half
years or
then
nobody have
any idea what it's what the world is the
your profession will be like in in 4
years from now. So, it's really hard to
I mean to say, "Oh, yes, you can you
still going to have me." Because now
people say, "Oh, no." The the the
manual tasks, the AI is very good, but
it's you needed the the whole
architecture, you needed the
like a software engineer to do to
see the big picture, etc. That it's now,
but it you have no idea that that will
be true in 4 years and or 5 years. So, I
think I mean I like I enjoy programming.
I I could do I mean some people say,
"Oh, use the AI for that." I mean I
program because I like that. But exactly
but so if choose something that you
like, but really for if you are really
thinking about how am I going to live
with that? I have no idea it's really I
think it's a really
hard time to
to be choosing a profession.
>> Yeah, I mean you've worked on Lua for
such a long time. When you look back on
it, what went well and what didn't go
well?
>> We had this privilege
of
not having to satisfy clients.
So, we are the we don't have as I said
for instance, you can choose to add some
feature to the language because you do
not have a pressure, "Oh, we need that
feature that feature whatever it takes
or etc." So, we have this privilege of,
"Oh, we are not sure whether to put
that, we don't put that, we can wait 1
year or so." I think that it's it's much
easier to do a
a good project, a beautiful project. So,
I'm not I'm not sure this is a
recommendation.
Try to work with
without much pressure.
People usually do not have
this choice.
>> What was your measure of success if
you're working on a programming
language? Like,
you know, how did you know it was good?
>> It's more important to receive sometimes
that good people that I recognize that
as we like the the result than a lot of
people that I have no idea what they who
they are etc. Like so I I
I think this metric of quantity that is
the standard metric nowadays in
in the web it's got much worse that
everything is just in the number of
followers that me doesn't care who is
following you just as as many people as
possible. So sometimes for me it's much
more important if someone that I really
admire of thing all this that say
something good about Lua than oh we have
that many
But of course it's good also to have
some number of users and to be
recognized but I think it says a balance
between all of this.
>> Do you recommend people study other
programming languages to get better at
programming? And so question is you know
what are the top three programming
languages that you think every engineer
should learn in 2026 to kind of become
better at programming?
>> Haskell
I think it's a
it's an incredible language that it has
everything you need to
really learn about functional
programming.
I think one of the main benefits is much
there is a old joke
seen in the Haskell community that
if you write a program in in
Haskell and in C
in C
really spend one week
to make it efficient
and then you spend one year to make it
correct.
In Haskell you spend one week to make it
correct and then you may spend one year
to make it efficient.
Again it's not my joke but
I it has some truth not
always true etc. but I think it gives
the the idea. I think this is
maybe the the the main the most
important lesson of Haskell. But,
Haskell has many other
validity this thing about type
inference, for instance, that I mean the
entire language is built is
types are optional everywhere, and yet
it can do type inference for everything.
It can infer the types correctly, etc.
C or some
low language I mean, you can also have a
to learn some assembler or I mean to to
see you. But, assemblers now are
becoming too much complex. It would be
to learn like the
the 8080 assembler, very old assembler
of a very
but to have this exactly this idea of
what a machine does, how it does stuff
it exactly the basic level to have this
understanding.
Scheme is a language that I I like very
much because of this exactly this
economy of of ideas, very very few
concepts, and it can do some amazing
things with the
with very few concepts. The one language
that this is very very very old, but I
still think it is Snowball.
What was the first I think it was the
first languages to have pattern matching
and this idea of doing I mean, it's
really strong patterns, etc. And I think
it's sometimes it's interesting to see
old languages because exactly nowadays a
lot of languages tend to like I said,
the zero indexing that people
they copy a lot of they they tend to be
too uniform in some aspects. And so,
it's interesting to see some older
languages that have some ideas that may
maybe not even good ideas, but it's very
interesting.
>> Last question for you is
you know, knowing everything you know
now,
if you could go back to when you had
just started your career and give
yourself some advice, what would you
say?
>> To know a lot of stuff, you really have
to study a lot of stuff and it takes
time it's the
I I also joke about that people say,
"Oh, learn Lua in 30 minutes or learn
learn Python in 5 minutes or and I
always say that I wanted to
learn programming in 5 years."
That's it.
Really learn take our time. You have to
learn that and that there is a lot of
stuff
stuff to learn. There is no magic. There
is no
You really have to learn I mean a lot of
different things.
>> Thank you so much for your time
Professor. I really appreciate it. It
was a lot of fun.
>> Thank you.
It's all my pleasure.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebraker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides.
This is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units.
We're now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now. And so if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast, and I'll see you
in the next episode.